everybody it is Jack Murphy and you are
back on the Jack Murphy live podcast the
flagship podcast of the liminal order
you can find me on twitter at jackknife
you live at Jack arrive calm Jack Murphy
live all over the Internet's today I
have a very special guest to return
guest on the Jack moduli podcast is John
rabe and he is an author a military
strategist and a tech entrepreneur his
book is called the brave new war and it
has proven to be exceptionally prescient
and predictive we're going to talk a
little bit about that and we're gonna
talk about John's global guerrillas a
report which comes out every month on
patreon I suggest that you join it and
subscribe I've been a subscriber for a
long time and you can follow John John
rabe on Twitter it's at John rabe with
two B's John how you doing welcome back
very good thanks for having me back oh
it's my pleasure you know the last
podcast we did together was so
tremendously helpful for me and my
listeners I still get comments about
that all the time about how how
impactful it was and you know I've been
following your global guerrillas report
and that too is super helpful and
informative you're on the ball on a
number of different important issues
today so I really appreciate it you know
we're just gonna jump right into it
today guys if you if you want some more
background on John you can go back and
listen to our earlier podcast that we
did about a year ago so we're just gonna
skip the pleasantries and all that and
just get right straight into it John
it's been a heck of a year you've been
really busy what have you been focused
on in the last few days here I can
imagine the answer but why don't you
tell everybody yeah um you know I've
been writing the global Gorillaz report
for about two and a quarter years now
and this month I decided to do something
a little bit differently I built a
pandemic 2020 guide trying to get beyond
you know the kind of standard news that
you hear or see and digging into some of
the you know frameworks that would
actually make it more comprehensible to
people
kind of looking a little bit beyond the
horizon if I could in terms of the
corona virus and the global pandemic and
those shoes were correct correct and
that's an interesting approach for you
so it's kind of an open source right
I've seen that there are people placing
comments and stuff and you're sort of
collaborating with your subscribers yeah
yep I put it into a Google Doc and I
shared the link with my my supporters
and and they're providing me feedback
and insight there it's a pretty pretty
cool group of folks I mean you know you
have financial insight they have medical
insight they have you know insight in
terms of emergency response it's it's a
it's a pretty good group to be able to
tap into and they you know if I do
something wrong and they'll point it out
or the correct it or they amend it or
add a little bit to it it makes it kind
of a very cool living document that
people can use as a reference source
yeah and this is a very good example of
collaborative sense making and open
source intelligence gathering and I
think that you and I both have been
interested in focused on how how do we
individually and collectively as
networks and groups increase our sense
making capabilities and I think that
this is an excellent example of how the
power of a network can come together to
help not only the people who are
contributing but then the readers and
then your audience at large to so how do
you see that as it fits into sort of our
general war on you know confusion
information disinformation etc and and
sort of building those capacities for
sense making yeah I mean there's lots of
articles out there that point out that
there's a lot more false content being
distributed fake content spun content
and I don't really see that as a problem
I mean because I don't really think as
an individual anymore I think you know
in terms of a my network helping me
think through things so for instance
if I find something that I think is
credible and I think is interesting I'll
post it on one of my different feeds and
my network will tell me whether or not
it is there's somebody on the network
that that has more insight into that
issue than I do
and they'll they'll they'll set me
straight which is great because that
means I'm I'm not just one brain I'm
thousands of brains you know I'm as good
as the quality of my network in other
words right which is an interesting
point you know after we talked in in
March and my conversation is also back
then with Jordan Hall they helped me so
come up with the idea for the liminal
order and the liminal order is working
very much the same way that you've
described and in fact one of the one of
the key lines in my sales pitch for
people is that we're only going to be as
powerful as our network moving into the
future and this is a very interesting
example because in the liminal order as
well we have a dedicated coronavirus
room and we've had about 30 guys doing
you know just 24/7 open source Intel
work guys from finance and health care
and and health professionals doctors
investors people who are experts in
trade and global logistics and whatnot
and yeah we have just been collecting
information from all over the world and
it put us we think really far ahead of
the curve and people have been in
defensive financial positions and being
very aggressive with their their health
and the contact that they're making with
other people in in preparation and so
it's it's fascinating to me to see how
those conversations that we had a year
ago actually led into something very
productive that's working in the model
that you've laid out and others towards
being individuals being only as strong
as their networks and so congratulations
to you and and I find it personally just
fascinating and I've been reading
everything that you've been putting out
and so I wanted to dive in actually I
want to dive into the the corona for
sure but I want to back up just a little
bit because I know we can get bogged
down with the corona stuff and yep one
one of the things I wanted to talk about
before we got to Corona details
was your report about the sanctuary
cities and what I really appreciate
about your analysis there was that it
was not left only a right only and I was
wondering if you could sort of describe
for the listeners you know that report
but specifically around the Second
Amendment stuff and the immigration
stuff so if you could explain sort of
the the decentralized you know effect
that's happening and relationship to
sanctuary cities in our federal state
and federalism etc okay well um the idea
is that you know as we globalize the
legitimacy of the nation-state in this
case the United States is diminishing
particularly as it screws up a lot of
the things associated with globalization
is screwed up 9/11 by in by invading
Iraq and it and deleted a bit deal
legitimize itself by promoting WMDs and
not being able to successfully conclude
Afghanistan for example and then you
know the financial crisis in again a
goal lies financial system having its
way with us and in not being able to
handle the aftermath of that
successfully by punishing the fraud that
was rife in the system and states and
localities are trying to find ways to
adapt to that deficit and they have more
legitimacy than the nation does and
that's cropped up in a couple places
there's the sanctuary cities movement
began on the immigration side and mostly
from the left in terms of trying to
undermine any kind of immigration
enforcement and there were ways of doing
that and a most successful way was to
exploit the loophole exploit the the
federal systems approach to enforcing it
they they use civil laws instead of
criminal laws because they're easier to
to move forward with in court and civil
laws can
be ignored by the the states they don't
have they're not obligated to act as it
would be if it was a a criminal
enforcement action taken against an
illegal immigrant um and so you know
they were able to you know pump up the
idea that immigrants in California and
Chicago and other places can't be
detained because of that kind of that
kind of constitutional right that they
have not to be unlawfully detained and
and that's been pretty successful it's
spread across the country there's lots
of places to have it there's been a kind
of a an opposite movement from the from
the federal side to empower states and
counties to actively enforce on the
federal government's behalf immigration
law kind of deputize them in ways that
they wouldn't wouldn't normally be
deputized or you know capable of acting
so kind of a counterweight and you know
that kind of template then served as a
way to radically expand the the second
amendment protests right basically said
hey man if that's working sanctuary
cities is working you know it lets us
apply to Second Amendment issues and we
have a constitutional issue that that we
feel is not being improperly handled by
the federal government and it took off
throughout Illinois and then it went
into Virginia and now it's gone national
and again you see this state and and and
local level
kind of disregard for federal law
I mean basically they won't enforce it
and it's not so much excuse me
are there precedents for this I mean it
seems to me that it's like wow I mean
we're disregarding federal law to me you
know if you sort of a non contextual
analysis of that would say well you know
the federal government's falling apart
we can't even enforce federal laws or
protect federal civil liberties is this
a is this a new phenomenon where
local jurisdictions are just saying no
to the federal government in the last 40
or 50 years yeah but I mean it's it's
always been kind of a struggle between
the states and the feds all right you'll
see a lot of this though prior to the
Civil War
in terms of enforcement of what the
Supreme Court was saying what the
federal government was saying in terms
of how how slavery should be handled so
there was a go ahead it's very
interesting to me because I want to I
want to at one hand criticize the
sanctuary you know locality of sanctuary
cities and counties for for their
actions but then at the same time I
haven't fully support the Second
Amendment sanctuaries and their
disregard for the mandates from the
federal level so it's it's an
interesting place to put yourself sort
of tactically I guess where you can't
really criticize the sanctuary cities on
immigration well the same time
championing the Second Amendment guys
but but either way this is an example of
how this the power that was centralized
in Washington seems to be wrestling
being wrestled back by it by the
localities is this a trend you think
gonna gonna continue and and what is it
being driven by I think you know we both
know the answer but I'd love to just
explore it a little bit what is it what
is it being driven by and and where is
it going what is this gonna lead to well
all of this really cropped up after the
end of the Cold War and the kind of
unanimity and singularity of purpose
that we had during the Cold War in order
to win it was no longer needed
you know the extraordinary measures that
would you know the extraordinary powers
that we gave the federal government in
deference we gave them in order to when
that conflict was no longer justified
and the states are starting to do what
they used to do and they're starting to
diverge and getting back to where the
u.s. spent the first 150 years of its
history is in this kind of grand
experiment where there's thousands of
different experiments going on and now
to live and that's that's unsettling to
a you know kind of our modern
kind of way of thinking of things in
terms of this like singular strong
unitary state that kind of dictates to
you know all the localities I think
actually that this divergence is
actually good because you really none
none of us know how best to live in the
modern world and having a lot of
different experiments going on at the
same time is is a good thing right we've
we talked about before about how the
complexity of the modern age you know
makes both expertise and acting like
you're an expert or even incident you
know implying that you have an answer
one person or even one you know small
cabal people that that's sort of
nonsense and out the window I remember
we discussed before about how it has to
really be an iterative process of almost
trial and error and I guess by having
independent networks across the country
giving things a run and seeing how it
works and you know sort of testing new
ground in the long run you think that's
going to be a healthy thing for the for
the Union or do you think that perhaps
we're on divergent paths that this is
this new process is only gonna
accelerate especially with the
technology involved right well I think
we we have a flexible document in the
Constitution and it can allow us a great
degree of flexibility in how we move
forward you know this is kind of a
generalized model for handling complex
problems with me we live in a complex
world it's different than complicated
complicated is more engineering specific
solutions you know where we have all the
factors and we know how to engineer a
solution and we can we can build it
using a Barak bureaucracy and plan for
future events using a bureaucracy when
you get to complex things change
constantly and the plans that you had in
place or the system that you just built
can be obsolete at the moment you ship
it and if you restrict your your options
just just one or two expert solutions
you won't have the one that actually
works for this new situation and you
know when you're doing this at a company
level what you want you know you have it
facing a complex
market environment and you have a couple
expert solutions and they they main may
or not may or may not work what you can
do is open it up to the employees and
and the ones that gained a lot of
traction you know have kind of like a
hub sup as a port for them are the ones
you want to trial and not just
brainstorming things that go up on a
wall but I mean the solutions that
actually gain some kind of traction with
employees as a solution for this problem
and we're kind of doing that at a macro
micro scale with states and localities
going in their own direction trying to
find the the best way to not only
survive in this environment this complex
environment but to thrive right I've
been reading a little bit about
industrial organization and the future
of professional work and the author's
name is escaping me right now but I
think he had similar ideas I think the
book is called like reinventing
organizations or something like that but
he had ideas about how work should be
sort of atomized down to smaller and
smaller group levels with with sort of
general mandates and then allow each of
the small pockets of employees to figure
out what works best and then they can
then you know select from best practices
there which which reminds me of
something that you wrote about in your
one of your reports on China and talking
about how that the answers to these
complex problems are on the in the edges
and in the edge cases yeah and and
unfortunately also on the edge is is
closest to can to chaos right so in some
ways we have to facilitate and expect
chaos how does that work here in the
United States is that working for us how
is that working in China what what have
you seen as relates to you know needing
needing to have people on the edge edge
cases in order to come up with solutions
for complex problems well I mean we saw
a pretty amazing example of that with
China and the coronavirus so the during
the first month when doctors were
discovering you know infected cases and
getting infected themselves they tried
to raise the alarm
and they were shut down in the the
government the local governments in
particular were the ones who are saying
hey if you talk about this we're gonna
put you in jail and locked him up and by
the time the virus got you know got to a
level where it was picking up attention
at the national level it was out of
control
and you know all those people died as a
result of that and we have a global
pandemic as a result of not being able
to have those kind of edge voices and in
the States we're saying it it you know
in an interesting way with the way we're
discussing solutions to the pandemic
right now is it's very chaotic but a lot
of information is being developed and
discovered the whole problem space is
being unearthed there's some and
disinformation out there but that's fine
it usually is debunked if we think as a
network right there's some expert or
somebody who has some insight that would
probably debunk something that comes
across your your feed that's that's
wrong and then we're we're actually
running a decentralized response right
now right and it will find out what
works and what doesn't work in the
mitigation space I think that's a more
robust way of doing it because that you
might get it wrong if you did it in a
centralized maybe the quarantine
approach is actually the bad way to do
it interesting so what role does the
central government what role does Donald
Trump have in this I think people have
been criticizing him for like taking
sort of the I remember when George Bush
after 9/11 was like everything is fine
just go shopping right right and and
Trump's like hey it's just a flu don't
worry not a lot of people are gonna die
everything's gonna be okay what what is
what becomes the role of the figure the
you know the leader of the biggest
centralized effort that there is right
at the federal government right when at
the same time this the answers that are
being sourced in an open source
environment and networked environment
like we have here great well I'm working
on a
kind of an idea as to what should be
done at the federal government level
right now but I mean it's not like this
is our first rodeo with us I mean we had
9/11 and the you know economic crash
that followed that then we had the
financial crash and they you know
economic crash that followed that and we
had inadequate responses by the feds in
both instances now we have this and this
is you know going to cause a severe
economic dislocation
I mean recession on the edge of
depression it's gonna be really bad I
mean when you see empty flights and
empty empty tourist locations and people
aren't going to conferences and
conferences are being canceled it's
going to have a bad bad effect on the
economy
so can we what you can actually drill
drill down on that for one second yeah
sure so your predictive capabilities are
well shown and well proven and you're a
very serious guy with a very serious
background and I know you take your work
very very seriously so when you're
telling me and now everyone who's
listening that the potential economic
dislocations go even perhaps beyond
quote recession and veering towards big
d depression I think that that's going
to get a lot of people's attentions can
you sort of drill down on on that and
what's driving your analysis there okay
because you know that's that's pretty
heavy job okay
well we're seeing it in a you know in a
visceral sense in all the closures and
empty flights shutdowns have conventions
I mean conventions in many cities across
the country or a lifeblood of the city
right I mean in all the businesses
associated with you know servicing that
that need and then
that I mean that's just--that's the
that's the front end of it and it this
is of indefinite duration okay and we
assume that it's probably going to take
a couple weeks but that's not all the
indications I'm getting is that it looks
like it's going to run for another ten
to twelve weeks in this cycle and then
we back again in the in the fall in the
second wave right and that kind of
closure that kind of dislocation
economic dislocation at this level will
have debilitating effects a you could
see it on the individual level where a
lot of people are just you know losing
their jobs outright I mean you know we
don't need you particularly in the kind
of you know retail service industries
where where you don't have the kind of
protection a salaried employee has you
know you're being cut and a lot of
cities and local governments are
thinking hey how do we cash in on all
this sick leave that's coming up and do
we have to pay for that maybe we can you
know we're gonna have some problems with
tax receipts going forward maybe we can
recoup some of that by putting these
people on indefinitely if I know in the
airline industry they're going to riff
everybody and it would be the standard
of you know when we start hiring again
we'll bring you in
based on your line number and that could
that could last you know two three years
and I've seen that happen in the airline
industry quite often tourism is a big
industry it's like what ten percent of
the global economy yeah yeah I just saw
numbers like twelve percent yeah if you
look everywhere it's done cruises done
every company I know is also cut travel
budgets a zip yeah and offices are
closing travel budgets are closed I mean
South by Southwest was just cancelled
right you know that's a hundred thousand
people 315 million dollars going into
the city of Austin that's not happening
and every day I mean every day there's
more more closures and now with the
financial crash of 2008 that was like
that was a real hit to the
me in that you know the lending stopped
and the the velocity slowed and
investment then you know ceased
afterwards and the real-estate market
just completely crashed it cetera which
to me felt like yeah there was a global
crisis but it also was like a
fundamental economic issue right is this
the this to me seems like an outlier
event that's not actually representative
of the economic fundamentals am I wrong
in thinking that something that can be
processed or I think I think that the
thing that unites all three events is
that it's based on uncertainty and
uncertainty is like poison it's like
that the most aggressive acid on any
kind of investment in confidence and
confidence is the thing that drives
markets and it drives economic behavior
and if you are uncertain about your
future you know both your health future
as well as your economic future because
everything is closing and you're not
you're battening down the hatches
because you don't want to get exposed to
anything it it it has to have a
fundamental impact on the economic
system I mean there's there's ways
around it I mean and I was writing this
morning about you know the opportunity
for safe safer Trump if he wanted to is
to kind of rewrite the the whole
equation about stimulus right we've been
going that kind of you know stimulate
companies and bail them out route for
quite a long time it doesn't really
stimulate much and we saw that after the
financial crisis it's really it takes
forever to recover from these events
based on the way we've been stimulating
and and we're in a unique situation
right now where we have you know 30-year
bonds creating it you know percent and
it basically the global financial big
pot of money is throwing money at us and
said please PLEASE borrow from us and if
you you know really want to stimulate
the economy an emergency like universal
basic income thousand bucks a month for
all adults wait for two years to get us
out of this not perpetual not
not a new kind of social program in that
regard would would zoom the economy and
you could you could pay for it for two
years for a little over 40 billion a
year and then repay it in 30 years ya
see it repaid and repay the the original
amount of little over four trillion in
30 years with the economy that's was
vastly larger and then also after
reflection events because of the growth
that you're gonna get right so you
couldn't perpetually borrow at this rate
once you start doing this almost all the
projections I've seen where you don't
have to raise taxes in order to pay for
it give you extraordinary growth we
could have eight to ten percent growth
with it with a ubi and so we the first
year would be up but you'll be buffer
and and help people get through the
pandemic intact
so that we reduce the bankruptcies keep
people spending and more confident and
then when we come out of it this either
this fall or the year after
with the second year of ubi ban the
economy just zooms and we have a really
strong robust economy right out of the
gates giving us you know getting us not
only back to where we were but well
beyond that I think that's a pretty in
Trump did that man he'd just walk in and
in November it wouldn't even be that
people would forget the whole pandemic
problem they'd be like oh my god well
that would be a completely like
wholesale change in the way that we've
handled financial crisis and other
crisis in the past I think and it would
be amazing to me and in fact if you did
do that and you look back in twenty
years that would be just a monumental
actual change in the way that we
perceive each other and the economy and
the bailouts I think I think the the the
opposite case hand out you know a
trillion dollars to your corporate
buddies and and hope that they don't
just dish it all out and bonuses is a is
a failed a strategy that didn't have the
desire
outcome or at least not the outcome that
the citizens of the United States the
United States wanted perhaps the
architects of the bailout got what they
wanted but in this case it would
certainly be in the same vein as a
quote-unquote populist solution giving
power to the people here but John this
this seems to me to be a dramatic
response and I don't know that we've
made the case yet in numbers in terms of
what the crisis is going to look like do
you have any estimates on what this
could do to unemployment rates GDP
growth inflation in general and
investment rates like if we don't do
anything are we talking about 15%
unemployment all of a sudden are we
talking about you know GDP going into
negative 2 3 4 5 like what's gonna
happen if we don't do anything this is
pretty unique I mean when we get to
quarantine or quarantine or not and you
look at China and its quarantine it has
had a devastating effect on its economy
people just are locked in their
apartments and quantifying that using
you know based on the Chinese experience
is tough because they don't share the
numbers we're at this point in the we're
at the point we're at and the crisis
right now can go to different directions
we could end up in a quarantine which I
don't think is going to happen give us a
the way the feds are running it which
that sound virtually all economic
activity in in big regions and if those
regions are in unsuccessful and
containing the virus it could go
national like it they did in Italy the
other option is that they keeps on
running in and we see shuts downs at the
local level and those continue and
basically all schools go online you know
I'll travel across to a stop all of this
kind of activity that we normally see in
the the economic system dries up and
people start holding back their their
their incomes and and in fear that they
may
not have that income in the future and I
I don't know what the economic impact of
that is I I do know that it would be
horrific
and I don't haven't seen any modeling
that would suggest exactly what would
happen we're in uncharted territory I
mean this is a I mean this cut the
interesting thing about this this
pandemic is it it's not just like you
know the Spanish flu and how its spread
I mean this thing is going across the
world at a record pace it's and even if
you eradicated in your country it's not
eradicated around you you can come back
and spread just as quickly as soon as
you lift at quarantine it's a it's a
it's a it's a wild thing and and because
it's unique you know a modern economy
experiencing this kind of event raises a
the situation to a level of uncertainty
has to be it's a suppressive of economic
activity you can see already in the
finance financial markets the
uncertainty is causing all sorts of
instability right I mean you could see
it in the in the rate for the 30 year
Treasury bond right I mean they expect
us to do very very badly if you're
expecting a 1% return over 30 years so
yeah it's the first time the yield
curves ever been entirely under 1% as
far as I understand it yep so the
expectations of everybody is that we're
gonna get clobbered and and we're gonna
be get clobbered for a long time do you
remember when inflation was the big
thing everybody everybody they were
worried about you know since 1981 the
inflation expectations and scares have
been pushed into the background and at
this point now it's just like please
everybody take all the money in the
world and spend it and we still aren't
going to have any inflation it's
interesting to consider this current
event in the context of like the the
deflationary you know generation era
that were basically right like last 4050
years but don't want spending it it's
that the crazy thing is that here we're
having people throw trillions at us tens
of trillions if we wanted it and we're
not spending it on anything it's based
on you know we have this kind of old
model of thinking about
you know how you repay it and you know
getting locked in and and and they're
like I mean if somebody offered me a
trillion dollars a less than 1% as a you
know as a business man I mean I would
say okay I would take it a second and
then I would invest it in ways that
would yield incredible returns I mean
it's just like it's it's if dumb money
is thrown thrown at you got to take it I
mean I raised 5060 million bucks in the
past and it if it was as dumb as this I
would have I'd be a billionaire or
trillionaire right now
all right so and we're not doing we're
not taking advantage of the situation
it's like they're everyone's just locked
into this old way of thinking and and it
just it's just mind-boggling that the US
can't find a place to put a trillion
dollars that will yield more than 1%
right that that is sort of an insane
thing to think and but this act trend
has been going on for some time as a
matter of fact the corporate balance
sheets been carrying so much cash they
don't even know where to put it and
they're the ones who will have their ear
closest to what my metaphors are gonna
mix up but that you're closest to the
ground there we go
and they're the ones who are like
feeling the pressure constantly to
return
you know rewards greater than just me a
passbook the interest rates right and
they they can't find a place to invest
it so I'm not entirely surprised that
the federal government can't figure that
out either but it does seem to me this
would be a wonderful opportunity for a
bipartisan infrastructure bill that you
know raised you know however many
trillions to invest in something that's
going to yield long term you know
dividends to the United States amen if
you do ubi there will be enough people
at the local level being able to pay
taxes and do things that you get a much
better infrastructure build-out I mean
what happens at the federal level is
they start doling it out to the same you
know crony right businesses and and you
know 60 70 % of that ends up in the same
you know super wealthy pockets and and
and nothing gets super wealthy but they
don't they don't spend the money man if
you have a lot of one thing you find it
when would people have a ton of money is
that they they don't invest it in in
things that grow
at normal rates they end up either
locking it down to you know ensure that
they don't lose it
you know hedge hedge hedge or you you
gamble and it is usually the financial
Gamble's because there's only only
financial gambling a you know betting at
the global market level is that it's big
enough to handle the kind of money that
you have so we got all this lost money
in the system right now and it's just we
put more and more and more of it every
year into this kind of big casino slash
hedging in parlor and it's doing nothing
well that's the only thing is doing is
generating profits for Wall Street and
the guys that make oh yeah that make all
that paper do you remember you remember
after 9/11 when they sent out like three
or six hundred bucks or something to
everybody yep yeah to me I was a little
younger then it seemed to me like a
crazy far-fetched idea that seemed kind
of stupid it was like what's three
hundred dollars gonna do you know for me
hey and then in this whole global
economy situation but somehow today it
seems to make more sense to put the
money in the hands of the citizens
rather than in the corporations and then
hope that the I guess what this would be
a trickle up trickle-up economics kind
of right yeah but think of it think of
it as a can 230 million adult Americans
figure out better places to invest the
money to get better returns over thirty
years or better better results based on
that investment over 30 years and
corporations and I think they can I
think I think you know they will invest
in themselves they will you know improve
their houses they will and we prove
their education they'll you know do
things and they'll invest it and it even
if it they even if they spend it on and
say a vacation or whatever it's still
you know better spent and a lot of the
things I've seen on the company side
right and and spending in our vacation
would help the tourists and travel
industry but interestingly enough that
Avenue may be closed off as a way to
rejuvenate the economy if people don't
even want to go out of their house
what is a what is a leading indicator
for us to watch to see where we are in
this cycle is it infections is it deaths
is it hospital bed utilization rates
what what what number should we be
watching to see if it's going up or down
so that we can predict out you know
however many months to see if the thing
is gonna crest or not well there's a top
level numbers infection rates number of
people infected but that's get screwy
because we don't have testing kits out
there in any kind of sufficient number
to actually test a sufficient number of
people and it's also kind of screwy in
the United States is that most of the
other places that had in a rapidly
growing numbers had it concentrated in a
single region or city and it was a good
indicator of when that city would
overflow because I mean that's a that's
when things start to really break down
is with this virus is that when the
number of people infected reach a point
where it overwhelms the hospital system
overwhelms the the health system in that
area and they start to have to pick who
gets treated and who doesn't so yeah
it's like when eighty percent eighty
percent of the people who get this won't
have serious problems they won't need to
be hospitalized might be as little as a
headache and that's typically people you
know blow fifty or sixty who don't have
any history of you know diabetes cancer
rust transplants transplants yeah
respiratory issues so that that's a good
indicator that the economy doesn't need
to fully shut down we'll still have
people out there doing you know
generating food and you know it's
delivering stuff because those are the
folks that would be doing it and they
wouldn't aren't gonna be Keeling over on
the job dead you know from from exposure
what what what yeah it's that top level
of affection number and since we're
multi region we have four different hot
spots in the states it's both offer like
a kind of international diversity
spots where a lot of immigration has
occurred mostly from Asia so it's like
San Francisco Seattle New York and
Boston and those spots are actually
where most of the cases are occurring
and they're wrapping up really quickly
when they get to a point where they
overwhelm the hospital system in each of
those spots then we have a serious
problem from what I understand our our
hospital bed numbers are like on a per
capita basis like the lowest that
they've been in in a long time yeah in
1975 it was 1.5 million beds and then
there was a consolidation wave now we're
down to like nine hundred and thirty
thousand hospital beds even though our
population is 50 percent larger even
more important as the number of ICU beds
so we have an expensive capacity of
around 90,000 and then respirators and
then there's another restriction as
servicing those respirators after
they've had an infected person on them
and what happens is that when the 20
percent who do get infected that need to
be hospitalized end up in the hospital
usually in those you know that those
target demographics 15 percent out of
that 20 percent you need oxygen and some
lighter care but so they have to be on
you know enriched oxygen environment and
five percent of that twenty percent it
have to be put on ventilators so that
could be you know five percent of the
all the people infected have to be on
ventilators and that's where everything
starts to really truly break down
interesting and in in Milan that here's
this you know the stories coming out of
the hospitals I mean Mons a first-world
hospital system it's really high-end
it's a it's a economic center of Italy
and you know they I've heard that they
had twice as many doctors as the NHS
does in the UK you know per Hospital is
that when they started we get
overwhelmed they had to make decisions
and who got the respirator and they were
basing it on efficacy and so you
a younger person say 25 with type 1
diabetes their epics you know the
efficacy of actually giving them a
respirator was relatively low so they
denied them access to it and gave it to
an older person that had you know a
higher chance of surviving so it's like
this is like the horrible nasty
decisions that the doctors were making
and they were like going they're getting
sick and they're facing having to kill
patients and it's not a good situation
to be in and you think you think we're
gonna be in that situation in the United
States at some point soon here yeah it's
really it's really close
most people would say that we're say we
can have two weeks behind Italy I think
it might be a little longer because we
have a kind of a multi region situation
going I don't even think you know as
this develops that even the you know
rural hospitals won't be that much
better off because they're they're
lighter on the equipment and lighter on
the beds ICU but it's and they're gonna
be swamped more easily I think if you
know it's really dependent now since
we're not seeing much action at the
federal level everything's down to the
mitigation level and we have kind of an
unique kind of situation in the states
is that we're sharing information on how
to shut this down and there's a peer
pressure and shutting things down that
propagate this virus far faster than
anyone else in the world and if we can
do it at the mitigation level that I
think that over the long term is more
flexible than the quarantine system and
we'll have less damage on our economy or
not and our society if that's the case
optimally and this is where I'm trying
to figure out this on my own is it
because I don't see anyone thinking this
through is that about a year if this
lasts another you know twelve thirteen
months before next year next spring
we're kind of it starts to die off for
the summer again is that our optimal
strategy is to try to become as immune
to it as possible because we can't shut
down for that whole period a dime camp
quarantine for that well you know 12 13
14 months right and the way you do that
you'd wait without actually causing
excess death is that if you have a
mitigation strategy to keep your number
of cases below what the capacity of the
hospital system is they call that down
you know cramming down the curve or
pushing down the curve kind of thing
right but you don't want to push it to
zero
you actually want a lot of the people
who are not in the targeted category
target demographic of this virus to get
the disease and get the immunity so with
that when it comes back in the fall that
they won't get sick and they won't be
carriers you get this herd immunity to
this infection such that in the future
were less vulnerable to this pandemic
right so you know it's hard to actually
you know keep it going at a level that's
just below the level of the hospital
system I see you see what I mean I mean
it's yeah that's a very interesting
analysis to make like how do we make
sure just the right amount of people get
sick right rather than trying to drive
it I mean I don't think an under
mitigation strategy we're gonna able to
drive it to zero like a or close to zero
like a quarantine so could you define
what you mean by mitigation strategy
yeah there's this for different there's
a lot of terms being thrown around and
for what I could dig in you know based
on that you know the most cogent experts
on the topic there are four different
levels of response or a society can make
against a pandemic and the first layer
is mitigation which is mostly done at
the decentralized level it's social
distancing it's companies saying it work
online go home
it's a events being canceled its people
not shaking hands and not giving hugs to
people they meet in the street that kind
of thing that's what we're doing right
now and we're working out all the ways
in which to in you know do that most
effectively and then and then kind of
enforcing it a little bit through kind
of peer pressure and that's moving at
the speed of you know online thought
right
and the second layer is containment and
usually that is travel restrictions for
the most part it's done at the
governmental level usually the federal
and is in the US case it would be say
nobody from China can come here in less
stay or that first you could say nobody
from China can come here directly or you
could say they could be you have to be
put into isolation for two weeks that
can slow the rate of propagation of the
virus then layer after that is isolation
and usually that's connected to contact
tracing and you know investigative
technique and and it that means
basically if you have the virus you're
there hospitalized or if you're not that
sick you're still isolated or if you're
suspected to have the the virus because
you were you had a contact you would be
put into isolation now that can be done
voluntarily or in the case of what they
did just recently in New York and New
Rochelle you know with the National
Guard around is they have people that
probably won't respect that isolation
order right so they've got to put them
in a facility and input National Guard
around it and say don't move for two
weeks all right gang and then you have
the the fourth layer and this is the one
this is the quarantine and this is when
everything else failed and you totally
screwed up and everything's about to you
know the wheels are about to come off
the bus and then you say everybody in
this inside this geography this region
this country whether you have the virus
or not or whether you're exposed or not
it doesn't matter your movement is
restricted and then you know the way the
Chinese did it they put under they put
915 million people under some level of
quarantine Wow
yeah it's an absolutely amazing thing I
mean it's a scary thing because I don't
know how they turn it off they did it
this is kind of cool as they they used a
what they called the grid which is they
had local leaders who were in charge of
anywhere between 15 to 20 all the way up
to a hundred people you know they had to
manage their contacts and
and just make sure that they got food
and water and these grid leaders you
know propagated on a decentralized
fashion all the way across the country I
mean through the party apparatus and
then they had Wow yes cell phone apps
that would tell you when you could go
out of your house usually it's either
every two days you would have Brett you
designate one person to get a pass to
leave and then go get food and they come
back some cases it was once a week you
go out get some food and come back it's
a it's a pretty pretty austere kind of
thing it's like very centrally
controlled yet also operating at the
local level work you know every town was
setting up its own like entry system and
allowed to do that you know checking
people for temperature and they're like
that's a really harsh quarantine and
then there says this weird kind of new
middle ground that Singapore started
putting in place the kind of
interventionalist kind of mitigation
strategy and where they are constantly
peppering people with reminders of to
wash their hands and stuff watching
their behavior online using CCTV you
know even calling people out and you
know physically and accosting the time
that change your behavior constant
testing temperature testing and in every
location so you can't really go into a
building without being tested and then
just you know social distance
maximization they've been pretty
effective in in mitigating it mitigating
the the spread of the virus using that
extra governmental add-on but that
that's a level of control that we
probably never see in the states that
requires a super competent kind of city
level government hey I don't know of any
city level government that could pull
that off let alone national right so do
you think that the the mass quarantine
you know possibility is is definitely
ruled out for our here in the u.s. I
want to say definitely ruled out I think
well it's more likely if it does occur
it will be at the state or city level
right and then it will be instituted by
the state or city government and they
could they could
just say you know if it's New York they
put a ring around it and say no one in
and out and then they have to figure out
how to get the the supplies in and out
it's gonna be a mess and you know if the
stuff leaks out like it did in Italy you
know Italy had this regional quarantine
coming you know about to be put in place
in the in the information leaked out and
the north is full of people from the
south of Italy working there because
it's the income czar better and as soon
as the information leaked out they went
back they headed south in droves you
know that the quarantine is about to
lock them into the north and it spread
it throughout the entire country and
they said okay well we're gonna have to
expand this quarantine to everywhere so
if you do it wrong you spread the virus
everywhere and I'm sure they went
outside of the country to is you know
it's a you can turn it into a mess what
what sort of confidence level are we
talking about here with these
predictions I mean is this a 80% 90% 5%
are we wild-ass guessing here John or is
this yeah you have a high high factor
confidence factor here um yeah I'm
pretty I have a pretty high level of
confidence that we're gonna run into a
lot of the stuff I'm talking about
because I mean it's not like this hasn't
happened in other countries just around
us in the last month I mean I mean China
didn't just do this it's not like right
and we saw China do that and it shows
that there this virus is serious and
it's not just the flu you want to see a
country you know lockdown 915 million
people and go through the problems that
went through and it is going through for
something that just foolish you know and
you're seeing that the same thing in
Italy when they saw it because they put
those things in place because they saw
these hospitals overwhelmed they saw
they saw people dying in the hallways
and there were stacking bodies and they
go if this starts if this keeps going at
this rate here and spreads to the rest
of the country we're gonna have millions
dead and you know in these target
demographics now I can see a lot of guys
I mean you know doing the Elan musk you
know
mail thing it's like this is no big deal
it doesn't affect me you know I'm not
I'm not gonna get sick my chances of
getting sicker really low and if I do
get sick man you know it it might be
just a cough or headache and that's
probably true but if you care about
other people who are older I mean I have
you know I have a mother you know a
little older and she would be in a
vulnerable population I have I have a
daughter who has type 1 diabetes had it
since she was 2 and she's an operating
room nurse so I'm kind of I have a very
worried that she's going to be put in
the crosshairs on this so I'm concerned
and I'm trying to take measures to make
sure that they're protected and isolated
from this extent possible right
it's it really when you asked when you
see people say their level of concern
over this it often it goes from 2 to 8
or 9 and you know you can see the all
the twos are usually younger you know
guys that like you know they live in
pretty much alone they really don't have
that kind of fear there you're not
having to care for people you know you
know and then you have the older ones
who have kids or have with problems and
you have you know caring for older
parents and the like and it's like ok
that that's when the fear goes up and I
can understand both perspectives but I
think the more conservative approach is
to you know preserve the life and
probably the best way to go right I mean
I'm telling my kids everything's gonna
be fine don't worry you're totally
healthy you'll be fine you'll brush it
off it's not a big deal
oh it's even better for kids under 15
yeah they can't even detect the virus in
those kids right it's awesome it's like
the nestling news but then they say well
what about grandma exactly exactly so my
mom my mom is uh she's a medical doctor
and now a hospital administrator so she
likes she's she's crosshairs she's in
the crosshairs and she has a she has a
crew scheduled in like two weeks that's
been on the books from like happy here
and I'm trying to talk her talk her out
of going but she's not well the CDC
already said they would not recommend it
any when using you know go on cruises
they said yeah that's kind of like a
hazard right now most of these things
most these big events are canceling
because
people are doing you know voting with
their feet right so when you lose more
than half of the audience or most half
the people on the crews have opted out
do you continue to do the crews or you
do continue to hold the event and do it
as a run it out of los or do you cancel
it yourself so I think we're talking
about varying levels of effect here
right where we're thinking about who's
gonna get sick who's gonna get treated
and who's gonna end up dying there's
that level and then there's the second
second and third level effects of what
happens to the economy and you know
interestingly enough with the economy
being so big as it is you know just
economic dislocations lead to extra
deaths as well too right right and and
then there's also the issue of the
medicine that we get from places that
are under quarantine or aren't producing
as much as they were before have you
seen any information or data on on
insulin distribution in manufacturing I
understand that there's a number of
insulin manufacturers around the world
but most of the precursors come from
China and that was one area in the lumo
order that we were really focused on
it's what are these you know second and
third order effects going to be you know
and do you see you know manufacturing
disruptions like that that are gonna
lead to additional distress economic and
medical here in the United States
especially yeah I think those are going
to erupt on a surprise basis very much
the same way that a lot of people who
consume masks and surgical gloves we're
suddenly surprised in the last three
weeks that they were all gone right and
we're gonna find that across the board
and in a lot of medicines particularly
life-saving medicines I mean this is
this is like okay we're talking about
things that the federal government can
do this is where the feds can play a
part of a crucial role it's a golden
opportunity to bring medical
manufacturing back to the states in a
crash program and then keep it here
because you could you have government
spending on health care and that
government spending on health care can
be used a lock in place
you know domestic manufacturing of these
items this is like a this is a safety
issue it's a it's a national safety
issue and it it would take billions to
get it going but it could happen really
really quickly and it would be a net
positive to come out of this with you
know more resilience and and more
capability to take care of ourselves
when the world disconnects because what
we're seeing is huge sections of the
world just kind of winking out and you
know if this happens again in the future
and it will I mean this stuff will
happen again you don't wanna get caught
flat-footed or what every time is it so
this is like that's a that's a thing
that trump could do right now the other
thing would be the ubi for the economic
kind of cushioning effects that people
aren't kicked out of their apartments or
in Italy they waived mortgage and rent
so they put a moratorium on that they
you don't have to pay that Wow cuz they
don't want people thrown in the streets
I mean because they can't work they you
know what do you do I have no idea how
you put that into practice but that's an
interesting concept
so what you know to tie this all in with
some of our earlier discussions right
the the the grand strategy with China
has been a failure as you so eloquently
put it worth earlier and in a previous
podcast and in writing and such and
remember I sent you also that article
China Shock Doctrine ended up speaking
to the author of that Samuel Hammonds
he's actually recorded a podcast it's
coming out pretty soon and and in
talking to him you know he really
emphasized how we not only offshored
sort of basic manufacturing but then
also like precision tool manufacturing
and then high-level stuff which
disrupted the iterative process between
manufacturer and engineer which has
really handy handicapped our ability to
produce important elements of the
manufacturing chain as well as in
national defense and whatnot and now
we're seeing that offshoring and
exporting our ability to provide
medicine and healthcare
all in the name of global trade and WTO
rules and China's ascension and all that
I mean is this gonna finally be the
wake-up call for people to understand
that you know comparative advantage
isn't always necessarily the best best
you know rule to follow and that you
know exporting all this stuff to foreign
countries that manufacturing is not
always a hundred percent going to be a
positive and that there's a real an
urgent need to like begin Rhian shoring
all these various elements of our
national security and our national
health is this going to be the moment at
which those tides you know change or do
we still have that long road to hoe
there
well you'd hope right hey
so I mean Trump is pretty much just he's
singular in his you know focus on that I
mean you look at Biden and he you know
he is go back to you know way was with
Obama and was with Bush go back to the
the old open approach kind of a legacy
of the Cold War where were the market of
last resort for everybody and we'll take
it we'll take the losses associated with
that because we're leader and we have to
do that so our return to the old order
going exactly the opposite direction is
is looming right and I just still don't
see people fully cognizant of the fact
that we're barnable yet I mean this is
like again you got to take advantage of
the the opportunities when they present
themselves right so like free money take
advantage of it yeah an opportunity to
point out that you know we need to
manufacture medical devices and you know
everything from masks and gloves all the
way through to key ingredients that go
into insulin and and and and the like
here in order to protect us in case
there's a global supply disruption well
this is like the perfect opportunity to
do that if you don't take on you don't
take advantage of the opportunities we
come out the other side a lot of people
die things go wrong as a result of that
and people afterwards
oh they're focused on other things
they're not taking heat you know they're
trying to recover and they're not really
even thinking through the you know the
ways to stop it in the futures you got
to get a strike when it top you know
when the opportunities presented you
know it does seem like Trump might be
uniquely suited to solve that problem or
at least move and move us back in the
other direction right now and you know
it's funny for anybody that's followed
or studied Trump for a long time you
know all of this comes from his
experience in the 80s in real estate in
New York and when the when the Japanese
bought Rockefeller Center like Japanese
buying Rockefeller Center and that
famous golf course in California and
Carmel in the name escapes me right now
those those moments you know stuck in
Trump's mind so so prominently that 40
years later you know he's still running
and appropriately and but maybe even
just accidentally on his part his part
but you know his whole his whole focus
has been on observing and understanding
how our imbalances with China are a risk
to us and it's just funny to me that it
was born all those years ago during the
80s yes it is New York real estate
experience it's so funny because I mean
it the kind of Reagan James Baker kind
of approach to Japan was the kind of
thing that could have saved us from this
problem with China is it I mean when it
looked like the Japanese were going to
eat the auto industry I mean James Baker
came over and said you know to the
Japanese I said hey I tried deficit with
you is 60 billion either you correct it
through buying more of our stuff for you
cap what you get yeah
if not then we're going to cut you out
we'll find a way to make sure that you
don't sell anything here and they you
said Japanese willing to work they were
willing to manage the situation and and
we got a auto recovery and now we have
auto manufacturers here in the states
that that wouldn't have existed
otherwise right and we had a total
abdication of responsibility when it
came to Chinese trade it was it was like
this kind of weird ideology that's like
it has to be this way you know every
through has to be zero barriers and you
know that's the only way to approach
things as a you know kind of this
neoliberal
perfect universe and it's never that way
it's like everything has to do there has
to be a pragmatic element I think that
you know what's uniquely American
American philosophy is this pragmatism
if it works do it all right you know hey
if you're locked into an ideology and it
that tells you that this is the only way
to do things your problem it's
particularly in this age and a post
ideological age your screw or not you
know if there's no Pat answers for
anything no too complex
there really isn't and you're right it
is I do remember the late 90s and the
just singing of this obsession and and
no questioning and of the of completely
you know open borders for for capital
and for goods and you know and for
people in many ways to and and in
speaking with same Hammond's from the
niskin in center he was he reminded me
of how back then you know there would be
conversations amongst sort of the
academics and elite some about whether
or not that this was a good idea and I
remember Paul Krugman said something
about like you can't talk about this
stuff in public because we don't want to
give the quote barbarians any ammunition
so there was even like a concerted
effort to like you know suppress counter
arguments to to the whole strategy and
it really does seem to me that the the
the politics in the United States from
90s the 2000s 2010 are all coalesce
around this central idea the neoliberal
ideas of lowering borders and such and
and and now we're really seeing all the
negative impacts of that and I just
don't understand don't I'm not sure to
what extent the this is information
that's filtered into the general
populace and into the general you know
people in the United States you know of
some of it's so esoteric and obscure and
it's economics and but people feel it
right they feel right on the ground and
they feel at the factory closed and
they're gonna feel it when they can't
get their insulin and so it would be
wonderful if we could turn this around
and turn it into something positive that
would continue this decoupling that we
need to have and the sort of
re-establishment of our independence
self-care really this is what we were
talking about it's like it's independent
self-care ability to defend ourselves
and our ability to take care of our own
health and and we're gonna use that to
transition into what what all of a
sudden seems a little bit mundane which
would be the current current politics
you know last time we talked and and
just observing your writings over the
last year you know you're very focused
on the network political movements
versus established political movements
and could you just sort of give your
assessment of what's happened with the
Democratic primary leading up into Super
Tuesday and and the coalescence behind
Biden and what do you what do you see
there and what is it portend for the
general election do you think okay good
I'd like to just add something to the
the last point you were making before we
transitioned yeah it's just it's just a
general philosophy about kind of
resilience in a kind of a connected
world is that you know I started my
stuff back with global guerrillas about
small groups of people being able to
disrupt the global systems and in that
disruption would percolate and cascade
throughout these interconnected systems
and a lot of people thought hey that
means that I have to become totally
disconnected I have to cut the grid you
know disconnect from the grid and and
produce everything myself and and my
philosophy on that after carefully
thinking about it and trying out
different strategies for quite a long
time was that you don't want to
disconnect from the grid you want to
connect with you want to connect to the
grid or connect to the the global system
on your own terms and it means that
you've got to take got to be in a
situation where you could take advantage
of all the benefits of being
interconnected but you're not vulnerable
to situations when it breaks down so
what is disrupted and it breaks you're
not just you're not destitute you're not
you know completely prostate or a
prostrate you know you know you're not
you're not falling apart as a result of
that disconnection
it's connecting on your own terms is is
keys you get the best of both worlds so
like for instance I have just just
putting into concrete terms I have a
generator and the whole house generator
so when the electrical grid goes down
that's fine my generator boots up it's
not that I'd want to have my house
disconnected from the electrical grid
right this is relatively cheap energy
and it's like hey why not take advantage
of it in volume in it I don't have to
maintain all of the systems required to
actually keep generating that amount
electricity so all the benefits with a
back-up plan with on my own terms
and you know that's generally the same
thing with life is you have to connect
on your own terms if you feel that you
know disconnection is going to wipe you
out
avoid you know just set it up in a way
that's not going to wipe you out right
but our our connection into the global
trade by our I mean the United States
into the right trade network was a was
absolutely yeah yeah it was not it
wasn't there were no turn turns or real
for thought put into it I mean do you
think in the do you think that those
guys knew did they expect or do you
think I'm just trying to gauge like the
general level of cynicism or greed that
was in play at that time you know I know
everybody wanted those those hungry
Chinese markets and you know got a
billion new people to sell bicycles to
or whatever but you know nobody thought
this through
like we just didn't know at that at the
time I mean the only people that were
really complaining really loudly
we're like the Black Bloc people and
like an Tifa which is really crazy to
think back on now that you know we've
circled coming around 360 degrees in a
way with with the protests there but
yeah it's it's pretty nutty to see that
Al Gore was the one doing the heavy duty
lobbying Congress to get the China
admitted into the WTO I mean and trying
to almost single-handedly is the one
that you know accelerated global warming
by 50 years right so right he obviously
didn't like think it through is that
you're transferring environmentally
protected manufacturing to a
a place that just will lift all those
restrictions and just do it as dirty as
possible is good it'd be a bad thing
you know it's it reminds me of how NATO
expansion you know how do we expand a
NATO up to the edges of the Soviet Union
or Russia
I heard that follow the Sun you Soviet
Union and it was under Clinton and they
traced it back he traced his decision
back to when he had a group of people
coming in to discuss ending genocides
which is interesting and then that you
hear this story is it well yeah I just
laughed because I remember Hillary
Clinton constantly referencing Rwanda
constantly referencing right yeah and
they he asked them what can we do to
prevent genocides in the future and they
said expand NATO all right and so you
know that was their thinking through
maybe the the Balkans crisis and they
were thinking okay if we had more NATO
members it would would have made a
better response and we but what ended up
happening is that kind of
spur-of-the-moment decision without any
regard to what would that would do to
Russia's behavior we expanded NATO right
up to their borders and and you know
radically give me anyone who's a
hardliner in Russia all of a sudden
became right the obviously obviously
we're corrected that the u.s. was an
aggressor right and then we that made
trying to not only did we screw up the
economic transition to get Russia into
the system we screwed up the security
transition based on a spur-of-the-moment
kind of thing and you know a lot of it
was like trendy academic theories and
you know philosophies that everything is
going to be interconnected and you know
yeah there has to be right without
thinking through the consequences of
disruptions and everything else but you
wanted to talk about top politics so we
probably should jump yeah we can do that
one last thing you know I'm not gonna
kill a good conversation just forever as
an agenda oh what's interesting actually
that popped into my mind just now as a
comparison social media right it comes
out everybody gets out there starts
screaming and yelling
exploring and expressing as Jordan Hall
says and it seems like this is the
natural course of action this is where
we should go this is the future yada
yada well you know what in the last few
years people have realized that actually
doing all of your business in public and
sharing everything in public and being
100% engaged in social media may not
necessarily be the smartest corner of
course affection and in fact and in fact
breaking off from that giant system into
smaller groups that are private with
high trust levels yeah are more
effective than participating in this
giant cacophony where there's a lot of
downside risk and it's an interesting
parallel to to globalization and the
path that we took into WTO and out of
the 90s and now here we are considering
whether or not you know as a rule those
sort of open exchanges are 100% an
essential good and are there ways that
we can do it more effectively a safer
and maybe even cheaper it's an
interesting parallel actually that I
hadn't hadn't considered until just now
but it doesn't make sense like market
evolution evolution of ideas etc it's
just the consequences getting it wrong
in the first place were so severe well
you know the breakdown processes is
pretty chaotic I mean we saw that when
the printing press broke up you know the
Catholic Church and feudalism and
instead in motion a series of changes
that you know built the modern world you
know built science and built the the
bureaucratic state built the the global
financial system as we see it and all
from that little printing press you know
just but the you know one of the big
trends that we're dealing with now and
you're taking advantage that is the the
this tribal thing is that you try being
up is a good thing said we're not solid
it we're not individuals anymore like we
were after the printing press when we
think in isolation we we learn in
isolation by reading and and then
we take a stand as individuals is that
we're increasingly part of a group and
that's kind of alien but it's it's more
survivable in this environment you know
if there's a lot of comfort in actually
having other people who are around you
that will will back you up and we all
miss that we all like we're all kind of
wanted I mean you know it's this is this
like this missing limb that until
recently you know you didn't really feel
because you didn't you know we're living
in a different world and now in this
kind of more a little more chaotic world
you're starting to feel that this is
this phantom limb problem yeah like the
lack of this kind of tribal context that
helps you know stabilize your life and
that's not all done out and they open
I'm you know it's not done through just
friend networks though you know friend
networks and followers and stuff are
great for vetting information and
introducing you to these people but
these people that are this backplane is
its key to getting through this intact
yeah I agree a hundred percent this is
basically one of the fundamental premise
underlying the the limo order and you
know tell them we uh we have a hundred
over a hundred and ninety active members
now and less in less than a year and we
are we are constantly discussing all
these issues whether it's a fourth
generation warfare where we're rebooting
our seminar on that we did at eight week
seminar yeah where we're looking at
we're doing like a logic class like just
how to think rationally and clearly we
have an active sense making apparatus
that's constantly processing information
and crowd sourcing and putting it
together into a useful and actionable
actionable information in fact you know
our coronavirus room we were ahead of
the market moves and many of our members
you know took defensive positions and in
fact we even have like fund managers in
our midst
they took defensive positions and you
know the the sheer number of dollars
that were saved just from the right our
sense making capabilities is so big I'm
not even gonna say it on the podcast
it's it's like unbelievably big yeah and
it's just it's absolutely freakin
incredible to me that these kind of
theories that we've talked about you and
I and me and Jordan and other people now
are coming to fruition in reality and
and and it's really happening and the
guys it's not only just the sense making
in the community there's a sense of
actually like a community aid mutual aid
- right like we've had members in crisis
and the holes the whole squad you know
rallies and chips in like 20 bucks and
awesome they've got you know two grand
or twenty five hundred dollars like fix
up things so you know I thank you for
those early conversations that we had
and certainly the guys in the limo order
a huge fans of yours and they they
really appreciate the work - and so
we're trying to be the living embodiment
to steal another word from Jordan about
a change that we wish to see in the
world today you know it's a it's very
baseline stuff but be the change and
we're doing it and it's it's fun and
it's out there and it's on the edge and
yet at the same time it's so necessary
and and feels very wholesome and
rewarding - so anybody out there that
wants to learn more come check us out at
the liminal - and order com like I said
we have over 190 members mostly in the
United States but worldwide and we've
had meetings in New York DC LA San
Francisco Denver Nashville Austin and
and they just keep in western New York
even that just keeps going so it is the
future and I appreciate your
contribution to that so but let's let's
get to the politics part I know people
are gonna be interested in that I am
myself as well so what is your
assessment in in the context of your
theses going back to brave new war your
understanding of the network to conflict
and Network warfare politically
political networks the open source
politics that we find ourselves in where
where are we today what happened before
Super Tuesday and what's going to happen
moving forward this is okay so you know
my first thing when I start or when I
started writing and as
independent person online and and with
my global Gorillaz blog and then my book
and then this I started focusing in on
fourth-generation warfare and the
premise behind that is that we were
going reversing the peace of westphalia
were going you know to the the error
that existed before that whether the
nation-state was in decline but well
what we saw as like this online world
exploded is that it was more just a
seminal event brought on by technology
that was setting in motion a lot of
different forces creating new things and
shaking up the old order kind of just
like the the printing press did like we
mentioned earlier and that the the
breakup that of the nation-state that we
saw in the fourth generation warfare the
primary loyalty isn't like developing as
in opposition to that was very similar
to what was going on with the Catholic
Church and and and the feudal system
when when the printing press made it
possible to you know start here on
Church I mean actually have a Bible in
hand right um so what we're seeing now
is some you know I've been talking a lot
about networks and and network politics
you know I started with this idea that
there are three different networks
competing that this network system the
social networking system plus everything
else associated with it online was a new
decision-making system a new social
decision-making system and we're just
learning how to use it effectively to go
along with you know markets and
bureaucracies and and kind of tribal
cohesion cohesion in the form of
nationalism those systems work well up
to the end of the 20th century and this
one was being added so we were in the
kind of training wheels phase or no
training wheels because we were falling
over all the time right and so okay so
he hit three big forces and forced on
the right force on the left and the
establishment
and the force on the right it wasn't the
kind of a classic conservative force it
was in this networked world it had a
different kind of form it was disruption
they broke down consensus or old
consensus so old ways of doing things
that were locked in place so Kitely we
couldn't even address them because those
assumptions were in not if you know not
questionable right all right stuff like
trade it's like right of course we're
gonna do this trade trade has to work
this way or you know a you know of
course you know we're not going to
change anything having to do with
immigration of course we've got to do
this or that it has to be this way
because this is the way we've always
done it and you see like little versions
of that with like Eric Weinstein thing
about the rat testing I think wouldn't
even change that basic little thing in
the rat testing even though it was shown
that those rats were biasing the results
because it was such a core assumption
right all this other research and
unraveling it was incomprehensible so
what so the right forget it
yeah the right formed kind of a
disruption kind of little little chaotic
at times but you know take those things
on and they formed there was a form of
warfare that allowed them to actually do
a successfully online a kind of a form
of maneuver warfare where you get a
rapidly changing topics and and
constantly attacking it from ready for
any different directions and that was
Trump's that was the network that put
Trump in office and Trump was more of a
conduit for making that happen then the
actual classic candidate in the kind of
literary world and what the assumption
was and my part was that there was going
to be a challenge on the left and the
left wasn't the classic like how much
more government spending there would be
it was more trying to set up a consensus
consensus that we can all agree on and
consensus forming around a variety of
just as really basic gut issues and
optimally if you could form a consensus
is that you can do other things as a
group and
future right now if you ask anyone I
mean I did a couple polls on that's in
it and I vote you know I asked you know
what do we agree on as a country mm-hm
and nobody can come up with anything you
know they like potato chips or something
like football but but even that's not as
as universal as it was so um um in terms
of doing anything as a government or
doing anything you know together it's
pretty much all over the map so what we
need to have in order to work as a group
though is is is that consensus and I was
hoping you'd see some of that on the
left like even if you know most people
even if you don't agree with it agree
that you know health care should be some
kind of right you know we should have at
least a basic level of health care for
people yeah you shouldn't be able it
just because you don't have a dollar in
your pocket you know you shouldn't be
denied getting some basic health care
and if you frame it like that it could
people can agree on it and then you can
start to build policy but we have we're
not even getting you know we're we've
been talking more at the policy level
which is hiring the stack and it's not
that's not something we can address so
what we had is like Sanders and Warren
and it looked early on that they were
gonna be able to do something along that
vein I mean Warren was great at these
big sweeping moral arguments right yeah
and you know mostly focusing her initial
work was all focused on the family and
that and and family incomes and how it
was impossible for them to get ahead
because of these cost structures and if
she had based her you know sweeping
moral claims based on that she probably
would have been a winner and the network
was could have formed around her and
what happened is that the the network
was divided into two pieces at Fort the
network there was a posting trump the
resistance forked into two pieces one in
behind sanders who was talking in more
sweeping terms using the night made us
kind of label it was it was had some
good pieces to it but it was still tied
to a lot of older policies and then
warren was more particularly she was in
she dived into the
intersectional stuff right very heavily
and that was more divisive you know and
that's not building that consensus and
the civil war between that I mean
whenever there's a fork in any network
it's usually the most vicious war it's
just that they're constantly there'd
it's not reconcilable and that tanked
the network left response to this
election and so the establishment which
is the third party uses their control
over the existing networks the legacy
media that the their ability to do
influence governments and the like or
you know local state and local level
as kind of a bludgeon well they were
able to consolidate based on their fear
that Sanders or would take over the
party and then they were able to fight
them off and it's been successful so now
we have a kind of a dysfunctional system
we have like a an establishment
candidate and the problem with the
establishment just like same thing that
face the kind of the Catholic Church
right after the Reformation started is
why do you exist you know why are we
supporting you and a lot of the
established market it says basically
we're not them or we can bring you back
to where we were or you know in Biden's
Casey says I'm more electable and that's
it that's the extent of their entire
argument they don't they don't have
anything to do any direction they want
to take us other than back no real
reason no real grievance other than you
know opposition to Trump brand right so
they're just so nothing it's a big
nothing burger kind of thing it's a
so you know that's that's the situation
we're in it's like this empty
establishment trying to rally around a
candidate up against the networked right
which Sela seems vibrant I mean they
tried to take him down through legal
campaigns you know all that all the you
know I was writing two years ago that
the you know all of this stuff wouldn't
work because you know the the Russia
Russia Gate stuff and then the follow on
impeachment wouldn't work because Trump
is immune to that because he's he's a
conduit for the network so they're not
at you know if you tech the person the
person is really not there
he's just the conduit for the network so
that every attack you make on him passes
right through it right you know and and
is exactly what happened it wasn't a
legal process it was a way of damaging
there's supposed to be a way of
discrediting or D legitimizing the
target and it didn't have the intended
effect and Trump ended the whole process
up the way forty six percent approval
really the highest he's been since at
the beginning of the presidency right so
um so now we're going to coming up on
election where there's not a network
left is gonna go sulk for a while and
try to figure out what is supposed to do
and they may end up tanking it by not
supporting Biden and then you have you
know Biden versus Trump up in the you
know establishment versus network great
so that's my that's my nutshell it's
gonna be interesting to see the inside
now it's it would have been more
interesting if the network left had
consolidated and taken over the
Democratic Party as decisively as the
network right did with the Republicans
but
they just weren't able they just weren't
able to pull it off they just weren't
well and and I would say good good yeah
you know partially because their their
moral compass is something that I find
abhorrent and I find you know
incompatible with American values in
general and so you know from a purely
academic standpoint it would have been
interesting to see how the Democratic
Party would have been hijacked however
I'm pleased with them running an
establishment candidate who's basically
Hillary who's basically Obama who's
basically Bush is basically Clinton and
so it's a very easy campaign I think for
Donald Trump to continue basically it's
just 2016 all over again and most of the
factors that were at play which drove
Trump to the presidency are still in
play either their trends that negatively
we're trending downward that favored him
or they were trends that were negatively
going negative that he has reversed
which also that in favor him too so I
think that there's a pretty good chance
that he gets reelected it will be
interesting to see what the Bernie
supporters do I do know that there were
a number of people who supported Bernie
in 2016 who then crossed over to Trump
after the DNC you know the convention
and all the nonsense that went on there
and and I've come to realize that that's
because the network left and the network
right have the same enemy which is the
establishment it's just once you defeat
the establishment what you do after that
is it's completely different policies
but you know the the idea that we're
controlled by a cabal of neo liberal
minded corporatist basically from both
the right and the left is is sounded
before like a weird conspiracy theory
but it's so plainly obvious and all
these issues we've been talking about
today are a result of that cabal the
China Ascension the global trade the the
neutering of our military capabilities
manufacturing capabilities and just gosh
darn friggin self-help and medical
CAIR capabilities all of these are a
result of the last four decades of
basically unified control even though
they both came from the right in the
left yeah it also points to probably
what who the next candidate to kind of
replace Trump would be mmm it's a I
think right now it looks like Tucker
Carlson I mean I me truly he's really
just he hits it like for instance
bringing back medical manufacturing I
was thinking that I wrote about it and
then I saw he had a show on that is like
that's right that seems to hit these
notes constantly he's got a better ear
for it then Trump I mean he's not as
good at the disruption element and the
changing the fast transients but I think
he has a better ear for figuring out
where that where the pressure points are
but that's me I mean this I I think I
don't see anyone else I could pull it
off I think here I think you're right
Tucker Carlson would make a fantastic
candidate he he may be even better
public speaker and order then then Trump
the way he can get people riled up and I
do appreciate and you know he does have
a network of people scouring all of
social media all of our work your work
so if you if you say something and two
days later ends up on Tucker Carlson
there's less than zero chance sit there
they're watching and observing and and
and taking information from but that's a
kind of a formal he's formalized to
process it of the network feeding the
candidate just like Trump was an
informal version of that you just what
he happen to see where they happened to
pick up but the Carlson's actually
formalized that process he's looking for
the good ideas to percolate pop up out
of this open source network it's pretty
interesting I mean that's a that's the
you know and exactly the opposite of the
left it the network left at least the
candidates that ran I mean there's no
way Biden would look at anything on from
Twitter and take it as as a good idea
you know or or Sanders or even Warren
you know I unless Warren had a lot of
not invented here kind of thing if she
didn't come up with the policy it's not
it's not good enough right so I I think
that the some of those people on network
left did take a little bit of
Twitter too seriously which i think is
the woke the woke element you know right
when they were all on stage and Bernie
Sanders goes America is racist from top
to bottom and and Elizabeth Warren says
racism is everywhere and getting worse
every single day I'm like wait the only
place they're getting that from is the
intersectional left the online
intersectional left it's because
obviously not based in fact but it is
interesting to see how you know I call
her mom Amy Amy mom she fell in line
mayor Pete fell in line they all fell in
line behind Biden who is by all accounts
clearly deteriorating right before our
very eyes he's not the same guy that he
used to be the cynic the deep deep cynic
in me thinks that Obama understood this
they're throwing a sacrificial lamb out
to be slaughtered here and saving the
Michelle Obama
you know campaign for 2024 you know
that's the deeply cynical part of me and
you know maybe it's right I don't know
time will tell I will definitely tell ya
a folded yesterday joined the Biden
train yeah I was like whoa yeah if I
were him I would just sat it out right
it's it's very interesting to see what
power gets wielded behind the scenes
obviously there and it makes all of them
sound like a bunch of hypocritic horses
asses because they just stand there
banging each other over the head and now
they're like this guy's the greatest you
should be president but yeah the 22
clearly don't believe it right you're
going okay he'd make a great president
even though you know it you know it's
not true right I can't honestly I can't
understand some of that but I do know
that Trump versus Biden is going to be
very similar to 2016 Biden I think is
even less of a qualified candidate not
qualified but a weaker candidate than
Hillary was and I don't suspect the
outcomes gonna be any different
interesting to bring up Tucker Carlson
2024 I think I could get behind that
myself yeah it seems like it natural it
seems like a kind of a shoe and he's got
that kind of it and the way candidates
are vetted now is that they're out in
public running their own show right
right right that's where you start well
you got your network and you go from
there yeah you gotta bring your own
network and you can say that about
basically any industry
at this brain so I've been able to do
that with just content creation and and
and being an author and a writer you
know if you build your audience then you
bring that audience to other endeavors
and people would then want to work with
you if you have the audience power it
then feeds on itself and you do a whole
podcast on how to develop that audience
power sometimes it's the straightest of
lines yeah that's also the way we you
build this a small business now I mean
you know if like there's a classic
example of you know jeans made to order
there was a little company that had
these like small runs of jeans and they
would do maybe 200 pair right and they
were pretty unique if you're buying them
in a city you probably be the only guy
in the city with those jeans and it had
its own denim and its own stitching and
everything else but if they had to do it
through manufacturing and you know in
the traditional way you take all the
risk and then you'd put it through the
retail chain and the jeans would cost
300 bucks a pop and so what they did is
they built a network of people yeah
we're interested in their jeans and then
they said okay who wants to buy this
they describe it they show it they
prototype it and then they people put up
their hands and if they got a certain
number of orders all the risk in the
venture was gone right and then they
just produced it with zero risk send it
out if there were any extras I mean once
they had the production volume up other
people would hop on it was it was a
great way to run it and and the same was
almost anything that you know that
thousand fan kind of thing sure I think
it's still you know about a thousand
that you you need to kind of become
viable yeah I mean I mean once you if it
depending on how deep you go
so deeper smaller number maybe 100 if
it's a lighter touch it's about a
thousand so you know you think of yeah
what five billion people online and you
need a thousand great become viable and
whatever niche you're focusing right so
the the world of opportunities out there
scott adams says we're living in a
golden age Mike Stern which the other
day said this is the greatest
opportunity
creative America's history you know some
people can look at the world today and
think that Hitler's running the country
and everything's falling apart and this
is the worst horrible most horrible
place in the universe to live the rest
of us are thinking that it's a world of
opportunity and a wonderful time to be
alive and there's basically nothing
standing between you and whatever you
want to do besides you're the only
obstacle so he just have to get out and
get out there and do it and number this
we're in the middle of where the future
is being made I mean we're running the
biggest social experiment in the history
mankind where we're trying to figure out
how to live on the edge of chaos
a complex system that's constantly
shifting every week it's a new thing
right every week there's a new challenge
and and things are just flipping 180
degrees out and we're trying to find the
way to actually live in that on that
edge where you get incredible
opportunities and you know incredible
changes overnight and you got to be able
to exploit them and take advantage it's
an awesome time to be alive it's really
amazing
you you know and also a lot of people
just don't step back just a little bit
and then look at your your personal life
outside of online and you go I know I
look at my my four kids and they were
all doing great and I did something
right with them and they're we're all
pretty happy and they're successful and
healthy and doing the things that they
they love to do and you know I look at
my domestic life and how that works and
I got you know oh yeah I'm very happy
with that so why should I be upset
online air about the world or you know I
would like to see things differently and
I can critique them but day this is an
awesome time to be alive it really is
and I like what you said about thriving
on the edge of chaos that that is uh
that is exactly right and you know the
name liminal order is kind of nerdy
liminality is you know transition time
between two fixed points and offers a
chance for for sort of remaking yourself
and coming out on the other end
you know bringing together the sense of
liminality in which that our society is
in right now and some sense of order to
it is is has become basically the the
entire thrust of my life and it's a it's
a fun and interesting and exciting place
to be and the fact that we're having
positive outcomes is just incredibly
rewarding and you know it all comes from
conversations like this John and it all
comes from you know being proactive in
building networks and engaging and
activating the networks and trying to
learn and refine and iterate as you go
and as Jordan said you know the team
iterates the fastest who does on the
OODA is gonna be the team that wins and
I feel like that we're on that that tip
right now and a lot of that has to do
with you and and the conversations we've
had in your writing so thank you very
much oh my pleasure I really truly
appreciate it oh one thing I would like
to toss in on the liminal idea is that
it's it's actually maybe a transition
from the solitary man to the networked
man to the kind of the tribal man it was
like moving from you know dealing with
everything as an individual alone in the
world to working as as as part of
something else where that those other
structures now you know you have it that
transition that you know solo you know
world the world of print and and and
isolation towards connectivity and
networks and working you know together
to get problem solved so I mean that's
that transition that face transition
that we're all in right now yeah you
know whether people want to admit it or
not they're in that transitional yeah
yeah and you know there's only a handful
of people that even can articulate that
at this point and you know it's these
concepts are gonna take some time to
filter down into the general culture and
our our lingo and general expectations
of the world so to the extent that you
guys the audience members liminal order
that you're with us on this journey
right now you guys are way ahead of the
curve
and it's a it's a good place to be super
high value drawn super high value from
you as always I've already taking up two
hours of your time so I'm gonna and wrap
this up and just say thank you very much
I really appreciate it everybody out
there you should get should start with
John's book brave new war you should
become a subscriber to the global
guerrillas report on patreon I've been a
subscriber for a long time and I highly
highly recommend it find John on Twitter
at John rabe with two B's and John again
just thank you so much and you know I
hope that we'll do this again very soon
and you know let's stay in touch and
just keep the sing go and I really
appreciate it sir oh thanks Jack and I
really appreciate the time you taken to
seek me out and get me a answering
questions yeah it's my pleasure and I
will definitely do it again sir have a
wonderful day take care your time
goodbye
[Music]
you